Hey, everyone, let's talk about one of the most basic words in English, can.
皆さん、英語の基本的な単語「can」について話しましょう。
Seems pretty simple, right?
簡単そうですよね？
You probably use it all the time without a second thought.
多分、何も考えずにいつも使っていますよね。
But what if I told you that every time you use it,
でも、使うたびに
you're following a secret set of pronunciation rules you probably didn't even know existed?
知らず知らずのうちに秘密の発音ルールに従っているとしたら？
Well, today, we're going to dig in and uncover them. Seriously.
今日はそれを掘り下げて明らかにします。
Believe it or not, native speakers pronounce this tiny three-letter word
信じられないかもしれませんが、ネイティブスピーカーは
in two completely different ways.
この小さな三文字の単語を
And it all depends on its job and the sentence.
全く異なる二つの方法で発音します。
Most of us just do it automatically. It's like a reflex. But today, we're going to crack the code.
それは役割と文によって変わります。
Okay, just listen to the two examples on the screen. First up, I can swim. Now the second one, can you
ほとんどの人は自動的にやっています。反射的な感じですね。でも今日はそのコードを解き明かします。
swim? Hear that? It's a massive difference, right? The first one has this weak kind of swallowed
画面の二つの例を聞いてみてください。最初は「I can swim」。次は「Can you swim?」
sound, cun. I can swim. But in the question, it's a strong open sound, can. Can you swim?
聞こえましたか？大きな違いがありますよね？最初は弱い飲み込まれたような音、cun。「I can swim」。でも質問では強い開いた音、can。「Can you swim?」
Same spelling, but totally different sounds, so what's the deal? What are the rules here?
同じ綴りですが、全く異なる音です。これはどういうこと？ルールは何でしょう？
First things first, let's look at the basic ability rule.
まずは基本的な能力のルールを見てみましょう。
Before we get too deep into the sounds, we gotta understand what CAN is actually
音について深く入る前に、CANが文の中で何をしているのかを理解する必要があります。
doing in a sentence. And most of the time, it's all about talking about what someone is able to do.
ほとんどの場合、誰かができることについて話しています。
Now, grammar-wise, CAN is called an auxiliary verb. Don't let that fancy term scare you.
文法的には、CANは助動詞と呼ばれますが、その言葉に怯えないでください。
It just means it's a helper verb. It can't really do the job alone. It needs to team up
これは助ける動詞という意味です。単独では機能せず、
up with another main verb. You know, like swim, play or read to add that meaning of ability.
他の主要な動詞と組み合わせる必要があります。例えば、swim、play、readなど、能力を表すために。
And the best part is, the structure is super consistent. The formula is always the same.
そして、構造は非常に一貫しています。フォーミュラは常に同じです。
You take your subject, add can, and then just the simple base form of the main verb.
主語を取り、canを加え、主要動詞の基本形を使います。
No weird endings, no ing, nothing. Super simple. And check it out. It works the same no
変な語尾やingはありません。とてもシンプルです。そして、誰が主語でも同じように機能します。
matter who the subject is. I, he, she, they, it doesn't change. Now listen really
I、he、she、they、変わりません。さて、これらの文でcanの発音をよく聞いてください。
closely to how I say can in these sentences.
I can play the guitar, he can swim。
I can play the guitar, he can swim.
She can read French, they can dance。聞こえましたか？
She can read French, they can dance. Did you hear that?
これらの文のすべてで、弱くて速いcanの音を使っています。
In every single one of those sentences,
これが私たちの最初のルールです。
I use that weak, quick, can sound.
単純な肯定文を作るときは、
So there it is, our first rule, cracked.
ほぼ常に弱い、強調されていない音のcanを使います。
When you're just making a simple, positive statement about an ability,
速く、柔らかく、文が自然に流れるようにします。
you almost always use the weak, unstressed sound, can.
さて、第一部は解決しました。単純な文は弱い音です。
It's fast, it's soft, and it's what makes the sentence flow naturally.
でも、否定形はどうなるのでしょう？
Okay, so part one is solved. Simple statements get the weak sound.
ここからが面白くなります。
But what happens when we need to say no?
段階を追って進めていきましょう。
This is where things get really interesting.
まず、肯定文から始めます。「I can use a computer」。
Let's just build this up step by step.
ここに弱いcanの音があります。次に、否定形にするためにnotを加えます。
We start with our positive statement. I can use a computer.
変化を聞いてください。「I cannot use a computer」。
There's our weak con sound. Now, to make it negative, we add not.
または、より一般的には、くっつけて「I can't use a computer」と言います。
And listen to the change. I cannot use a computer.
おっと、気づきましたか？否定形にした瞬間、
Or more commonly, we squish it together. I can't use a computer.
canの母音が完全に変わりました。弱い音が消えて、
Whoa, did you catch that? The second we made it negative,
強いcanが現れました。これは偶然ではありません。
the vowel sound in can totally flipped. That weak and just disappeared
これは英語の話し方の基本的なルールです。
and this strong can took over. This is not random folks.
否定形は自然により強い強調を求めます。
This is a core rule of how English is spoken.
さて、ここでちょっとしたライティングのヒントです。
The negative form just naturally demands more stress, more emphasis.
他の否定形、例えばdo notやis notとは異なり、
And hey, here's a quick little writing tip for you.
cannotはほぼ常に一つの単語として書かれます。
Unlike other negatives like do not or is not,
二つの単語、cannotとして見るのはかなり珍しく、
cannot is almost always written as one single word.
通常は特定の正式な強調のためだけです。
seeing it as two words, cannot, is pretty rare,
さて、肯定文と否定文は理解しました。
and is usually just for some very specific, formal kind of emphasis.
肯定は弱く、否定は強いです。
All right, so we've got the positive statements
では、質問はどうでしょう？次のパズルの部分に取り組みましょう。
and the negative ones down. Positives are weak, negatives are strong.
さて、この変化を見てください。単純な文から始めます。
But what about questions? Let's tackle the next piece of this puzzle.
「You can play the guitar」、これが弱い音です。
Okay, watch this transformation. We start with a simple statement.
さて、これを質問に変えるために、
You can play the guitar, that's our weak sound.
canを前に持ってきます。
Now, to turn this into a question,
でも、音がどう変わるか聞いてください。
we just grab can and move it to the front.
「Can you play the guitar?」
And just like that, the strong can is back in the spotlight.
そして、強い「can」が再び注目されています。
So the pattern for questions is super simple and totally reliable.
質問のパターンはとてもシンプルで信頼できます。
It always kicks off with that strong can,
いつも強い「can」から始まります。
then the subject, and then the base verb.
次に主語、そして基本動詞です。
This structure is like a big signpost that says,
この構造は大きな標識のようで、
hey, I'm asking you about an ability.
「私はあなたに能力について尋ねています」と示しています。
And what about when you answer the question? I mean, think about it.
では、質問に答えるときはどうでしょう？考えてみてください。
If someone asks, can you play the guitar? You'd never say, yes, I can.
誰かが「ギターを弾けますか？」と聞いたら、 「はい、弾けます」とは言わないでしょう。
It just sounds weird, right?
変に聞こえますよね？
You give it that punch, yes, I can, or no, I can't.
「はい、弾けます」または「いいえ、弾けません」と強調します。
So for short answers, both yes and no, we use that strong vowel sound.
短い答えでは、はいもいいえも強い母音の音を使います。
Okay, we've collected all the clues,
さて、すべての手がかりを集めました。
we've looked at statements, we've looked at negatives,
肯定文、否定文、質問、答えを見てきました。
we've looked at questions, and we've looked at answers.
今、パズルのすべてのピースを 組み合わせる時です。
It's time to put all the pieces of the puzzle together
これが大きな発表です。
into one simple guide. This is the big reveal.
ここにすべてが整理されています。 要するにこうなります。
And here it is, all laid out. It really boils down to this.
シンプルな肯定文には弱い「can」音を使います。
For a simple, positive statement, you use the weak can sound.
例えば「私たちは英語を話せます」が、 他のほとんどすべてには、
Like in, we can speak English, but for pretty much everything else.
否定文、質問、短い答えには、 強くはっきりした「can」音が必要です。
For negatives, for questions, and for short answers,
「彼女は運転できません」「彼らは歌えますか？」
Yes, they can. So, if you're gonna remember one thing, remember this.
「はい、できます」。だから、 一つだけ覚えるなら、これを覚えてください。
Think of the weak can sound as the default setting.
弱い「can」音をデフォルト設定と考えてください。
It's the quiet background sound you use when can is just a connector word.
「can」が単なる接続詞のときに使う 静かな背景音です。
The strong can is for when can is in the spotlight,
強い「can」は、 「can」が注目されるとき、
when you're saying no, when you're asking a question,
否定するとき、質問するとき、
or when you're giving a short, punchy answer. At the end of the day,
または短く強い答えをする時に使います。 結局、
this isn't just some random, tricky rule.
これはただのランダムで難しいルールではありません。
It's all about the natural music of the language.
言語の自然なリズムに関わっています。
The difference between the weak and strong forms of can
弱い形と強い形の「can」の違いが、
is what helps create the rhythm and stress patterns
英語のリズムや強調パターンを 作り出すのに役立っています。
that make English sound, well, like English.
この小さな詳細を押さえることで、 流暢さや自然さが大きく変わります。
Nailing this one little detail can make a huge difference
これで「can」についてはおしまいですが、
in how fluent and natural you sound. And that's a wrap on can,
ちょっと考えさせられますよね？
But it kind of makes you wonder, right?
「can」のようなシンプルな日常語が、
If a simple everyday word like can
これほどの複雑さを隠しているなら、
has all this complexity hiding just beneath the surface,
他にどんな隠れたルールがあるのか、
what other hidden rules are out there
私たちは毎日使っているのに 気づいていないのでしょうか？
that we're all using every single day without even realizing it?
考えてみる価値がありますね。 ご視聴ありがとうございました。